I want to talk today about behavioral finance or about
psychology and finance.
This is a longstanding interest of mine.
I've been involved with it for over 20 years.
It's not really emphasized in your textbook.
Fibozzi and his co-authors talk
about a lot of things in
the financial world, but not about the underlying human
behavior.
Behavioral finance or behavioral economics more
broadly is a kind of revolution that has occurred
in finance and economics over
the last 20 or 30 years.
And it remains somewhat controversial.
I don't quite fully understand the concept of
financial finance.
I don't quite fully understand
why it is that people polarize
as much as they do.
But some people don't like this.
Other people, I think, we're coming along to be the
majority, I think.
People are now regarding behavioral finance as an
important element of finance.
And so, the real problem is that people are complex.
And our financial institutions, as I've emphasized, are
designed for real people.
And their functioning depends on
the behavior of real people.
And it's not as simple.
Another revolution that's occurring parallel, of bigger
significance, is a revolution
in neuroscience about the human
brain.
And the human brain is a very complicated organ.
And economists have liked to invoke the principle of
rationality as an underlying component of their theory.
And that has been useful.
But it's of limited use, because people aren't rational.
They're often rational.
They're not completely rational.
And very often, people behave stupidly.
I'll put it that way.
That includes everyone, including me.
Because we're human, and we have limits.
And that encourages, one thing
about the human species is that
we are aware of other
people's weaknesses and have an impulse
to exploit them.
So, when you see other people behaving stupidly, sometimes
you think, maybe I can turn this to my advantage.
Okay?
And that becomes a problem.
The history of humankind is
a history of exploitation of one
person by another.
Not entirely, but I'm saying it
has that as an important element.
So, I'm going to talk about these human failings.
It's not to say that people are stupid.
I'm just saying they're people, right?
And we're all imperfect.
We're smart in some dimensions.
And we can be very smart,
but we can also make important mistakes.
But before I start, I wanted to
try to put this into a perspective.
Because maybe I'll return to this
at the end of the lecture.
But I wanted to start on an upbeat note.
I'm going to talk about all kinds of human errors.
I'm going to start on an upbeat note.
That the business world generally
doesn't exploit people terribly, I believe.
That very characteristically successful
businesses in finance and elsewhere
consider their long-term advantage
and the reputation they have.
So, doing something that is blatantly exploitative of
human weaknesses will work against their long-term advantage.
And so, we don't see, you'll see a lot of human failings, but
we don't see people cashing in on them as often as you'd think.
And beyond that, I want to emphasize also
that another aspect of human behavior is morality.
Evolutionary biologists think that this
evolved along with our other traits.
That we have an impulse to be moral.
And so, in the long run, you might not
really gain so much satisfaction from exploiting other people's mistakes.
And so, you don't necessarily do that.
So, that's why we'll have a lot of weaknesses outlined.
And we won't see, you know, we won't see
a lot of people who are not good at it.
And we won't see a lot of
people who are not good at it.
But we'll see a lot of
And so, in the long run, we'll certainly see
a significant or serious exploitation of them as characteristic.
Now, as you know, I have chapters
from my forthcoming book assigned for this course.
And I look back on what
I put up for you to read.
And I keep thinking, gee, this really wasn't ready.
So, I had a chapter for this
section of the reading list about behavioral finance.
I didn't really get it right.
I know what I was trying to say.
What I start out in
that chapter is talking about Adam
Smith and his book, The Theory of Moral Sentiments.
Now, just to remind you,
Adam Smith was a professor in
Scotland that in 1759, he was a professor of moral
philosophy, because there were no professors of
economics in those days.
And he wrote in 1759, maybe
I should write some of this on
the board.
He's probably the most important figure in the
history of economic thought.
So, in 1759, he wrote his Theory of Moral Sentiments.
And in 1776, he wrote
the more famous book, Wealth of
Nations.
So, this is the Theory of Moral Sentiments.
The Wealth of Nations is considered the first real
treatise on economics.
And it's a wonderful book, and it's still very readable
today.
Thank you.
I'd like to thank you for
taking the time to read it
today.
His Theory of Moral Sentiments is
not so widely read, but it's
not really economics.
It's a book about psychology and morality.
And I find it very good, even 250 years later.
He went through many editions
on this book, because maybe he
thought it was his most important work.
But the book starts out about selfishness and altruism.
And the real question, which he defines economics, is, are
people really completely selfish?
Sometimes it seems that way, that their presumed
benevolence is just an artifice for their own benefit.
But he wonders, how does
an economy work if everyone is
totally selfish?
And he ends up concluding that they're not.
I thought it was very
interesting the way he put it.
The thing he emphasized right at
the beginning of the book is
that people inherently love praise.
We crave the approval of other people.
And so praise is a fundamental human desire.
But then he reflected on it,
and he said, do people really
want praise itself, or is
it something else that they want?
And he said, well, think of it this way.
Suppose you have a
lot of people who are doing it.
And you find that people made
a big mistake and thought that
you had accomplished something.
But there was a mix-up.
It was really somebody else who did it, not you.
And it's just a complete mistake.
You had nothing to do with it.
But you find lots of people praising you.
Would that really be pleasurable?
And suppose you even know that
they'll never find out that I
didn't do it.
Well, Smith said, it probably isn't.
I mean, think about it.
I'm getting all this praise, but
I know I don't deserve it.
So I don't enjoy it.
And then he went on
to say that, especially among people
who are more mature, he says, more mature people, not
everyone makes this step.
But he says, adults, normal, mature adults, make a
transition from a desire for praise to a desire for
praiseworthiness.
I want to know that I am the kind of
person who will be praised, and
I don't need to get the
praise.
And he said, it's that tendency, ultimately, which
makes an economy work.
That people don't care just about praise.
He gives an example of mathematicians.
And he said he's known many mathematicians in his life.
And he finds that they're almost all obscure.
The public doesn't know about mathematicians.
They couldn't explain to the public what they do.
And they don't seem to care at all.
They don't seem to care about
the fact that they're not doing
anything.
They're doing something.
And they don't seem to care at all.
Because they know the public doesn't appreciate mathematics.
And so, there's a few mathematician friends who
understand what they do and may praise them.
But ultimately, a mathematician can sometimes do the work
completely unknown, writing.
And it's the praiseworthiness that drives these people.
So, I think that you may
think that I'm being too idealistic.
When I say this.
But I think that the finance profession, this is
what I was trying to say in that chapter.
That the finance profession, like other
mature professions, is really dominated, although
there's a lot of funny things that happen,
is really dominated by people who have reached
this desire for praiseworthiness.
And so, you're not going to exploit
people extravagantly, just because why would I do
that?
That's not a good thing.
I wouldn't feel good about it.
Though some people will.
Now, I wanted to also mention, not
everyone reaches this mature state that Adam Smith
describes.
And that's one of the complexities of human society.
And I think that the finance profession
has a problem with other kinds of people.
Now, there's a whole branch of
psychology called personality psychology that categorizes people
by their personality.
And we're not all the same.
In our society, we have
many different kinds of personalities.
A successful society promotes people
up who have the praiseworthiness desire.
We try to recognize them and we try
to put people of character into important positions.
With limit, not complete success.
But I wanted to just briefly talk about.
This is a lecture on psychology.
And I wanted to talk about other personality types.
And I was going to use
a book called The Diagnostic and
Statistical Manual, edition four, published by the
American Psychiatric Association.
They're coming out with a fifth edition in 2014.
DSM-IV is kind of a
household word around my house, because
I'm a psychiatrist, and my wife is a psychologist.
DSM-IV is actually controversial among
psychiatrists, because it's too cut
and dried for some of them.
What it tries to do is identify mental illnesses and
personality types in a quantifiable, reproducible way,
so that we can define, who
has this mental illness, or who has
this personality type.
And it's a checklist.
And it says, the patient
must have exhibited at least three
of the following five behaviors.
And then there'll be another checklist.
And so, you keep scoring.
You can actually diagnose personality disorder.
I'm just going to mention one.
They have many personality disorders.
One of them is called APD, called Antisocial Personality
Disorder.
And I don't know if you have
a checklist, but just to give you
a sense.
Oh, and the Antisocial Personality Disorder is called
psychopathy.
Or one kind of APD is psychopathy.
Another one is called sociopathy.
And I don't know, there's a huge literature on these.
But according to DSM-IV, 3%
of the male population in the
female population is APD.
And 1% of the female population.
A simple definition for APD is a jerk.
There are more male jerks than female jerks, apparently.
According to their, this is all quantifiable and done.
But what is an antisocial personality disorder?
It's a very common characteristic.
Lack of remorse.
Frequent lying.
Lack of empathy.
Superficial charm.
Shallowed emotions.
Distorted sense of self.
Constant search for new sensations.
Have you met someone like that?
You probably have, because that's 3% of the population.
I'm not anti-male when I point
out there are three times as
many jerks among males as females.
Females have characteristically
different personality disorders.
And you can look down the list.
So, it's much more than 3%
of the population that would be
diagnosed with one or the other.
So, you know what an APD person is?
Manipulative, feigns affectionate or warm
feelings, but doesn't feel them.
And is trying to deceive you.
I encountered one.
Once a student came to my office
and asked to sign up as my
research assistant.
And I was talking to him.
I thought, well, maybe, you know.
I said, come back and talk to me.
Later on, I read about
him in the Yale Daily News.
He was an imposter student.
He was not a Yale student.
And he had been around to other university campuses.
He was an imposter at like three different campuses.
So, there's something wrong with this person, right?
Kind of made me feel.
Then he came later and
asked me for a recommendation letter.
I couldn't believe it.
After I read about him in the Yale Daily News.
I said, well, I'm not a Yale student.
I could have just seen him on the news.
But those are, this is extreme.
Right?
And so, incidentally, someone did a study
of APD by going to a prison and
categorizing the inmates.
Using DSM-IV standards.
And they found that 40% of the prisoners had APD.
Also, neuroscience people have found
that there are differences in the
prefrontal cortex.
cortex that are correlated with APD.
So, it seems to be, it's
a problem we have in our society
that some people have a brain structure that's a little
different, and it may make
it difficult for them to behave
in a good way.
So, we're learning more and more about neuroscience.
And it's interesting to me that Adam Smith's book still
rings true, though.
It's a very interesting book.
And it's some basic common sense that we all learn.
You have to judge people,
and you have to learn their
character, and you have to be
a person of character, for in
the long run, that's what you want.
It gives you what you want in life.
So, I'm going to talk about,
I'm going to turn now to, oh,
another thing I wanted to
say at the beginning is that
we're all manipulable.
Unfortunately true.
And unfortunately, we live in
a world where it's hard to
avoid manipulating people at all, because we have a free
enterprise system that encourages competition.
And if the competition is manipulating people, how do you
completely stay clear of that?
And I think this is one
of the contradictions of our society.
And I think that's the key.
And a very simple and
obvious manipulation is, they'll put a
price on some item they're selling, like $9.99.
So, you ask, well, why
didn't they just say $10, right?
Well, you know why they didn't.
It's called pricing points in marketing.
Because $9.99 sounds a lot less psychologically than $10.
So, everyone does it.
Almost everyone does it.
But, yeah.
And I think that's the key.
Is that bad?
Well, it's bad in a way.
It's manipulative, isn't it?
I mean, I'm annoyed by it.
Maybe you are, too.
But if you were in
business, would you do that, too?
You might feel that you have to.
And it's a harmless sort of manipulation, right?
It's not hurting anyone, really.
They may be buying a
little bit more than they want.
But you see, that's the
kind of thing that comes in.
And in looking at financial institutions,
they're often manipulative in that sense.
But I don't think that
– it's similar to a politician.
If you want to be a member of Congress
or whatever, you can't say what you really believe, right?
Because you won't get elected.
You've got to kind of doctor
your opinions to the public opinion.
And so, otherwise, you won't have – but
you might have a moral purpose underlying it all,
because you want to get elected,
so you can do good things.
And so, you do end up saying things.
So, it's hard to judge people, good or bad.
It's an overall sense you get of someone's character,
that people are doing things that
appear somewhat manipulative and somewhat bad.
But you get an overall
sense of the person through time.
And that's –
and ultimately, our society, within
limits, rewards people that show character
through all the confusing details.
Now, I wanted to move – that was my introduction.
I wanted to move now to
discussing some particular aspects of behavioral finance
or more broadly, behavioral economics,
and about human failings that are exploitable by somebody,
and are somewhat exploited, but remain as –
I wanted to start out with what's
probably the most famous element of behavioral economics.
It's prospect theory.
And it was invented by two psychologists.
Danny –
or Daniel Kahneman and Amos Tversky.
And in the late 20th century,
they called it prospect theory, because it was
a theory of how people form decisions about prospects.
And a prospect is a gamble.
It's about people's decisions under uncertainty.
And in very simple terms,
the prospect theory says –
now, there's a huge literature on this,
so I'm trying to give you
a very quick description of it –
that there's something called a value function,
which represents how people value things.
And there's a weighting function.
And it's the two parts,
which shows how people infer –
how they deal with probabilities.
Okay, and I'll just show
simply what Kahneman and Tversky says.
I'll draw a picture of the
value function and the weighting function.
And this will be very quick,
and you'd have to read more.
But the way people value gains or losses –
let me see, how do I –
I better draw the line in the middle.
Okay, and these we're talking about financial gains.
So, these are gains.
And this is zero.
And this is losses.
Well, negative.
What I have on the horizontal axis
is wealth or money or something like that.
Zero in the middle.
Okay.
And then,
I have on this axis value,
which is something like utility.
I'll erase my zero.
It doesn't get in the way.
And what they find is that
people's value has a funny shape.
We don't weigh gains and losses linearly.
In a positive quadrant,
when we have positive gains,
there's diminishing value,
and we don't weigh losses.
It doesn't ever slope down.
It's concave down.
Like diminishing marginal utility in economic theory.
But for losses,
it looks something like this.
It's concave up.
I'm exaggerating a little bit,
but this is a diagram that Kahneman and Tversky wrote
in their famous Econometrica article,
a few years ago.
So, there's diminishing marginal utility for gains,
but there's the opposite.
Well, we have concave up.
And there's a kink.
You note that the value function
has a kink at the origin.
So, what does this mean?
It means,
okay, first of all,
this origin
is a,
what is,
from what point do I estimate gains and losses?
That's called the reference point.
And it's psychological.
And it's subject to manipulation.
The reference point is the zero
from which I measure things.
The kink,
so, first of all,
it's,
the reference point is probably today's wealth.
But it can be something else,
if people are manipulated
by the way something is presented to them.
Framing, according to Kahneman and Tversky,
is presentation.
So, I can give the same
prospect to people,
but word it in different ways
that suggests a different reference point.
And that will change people's behavior.
So, you can manipulate people by
describing something in different terms.
By suggesting a different reference point.
But typically, the reference point is today's wealth.
The kink means
that people are very conscious
of little changes in their wealth.
And they're spooked by them.
I'm really afraid,
because my value drops very rapidly,
even for a small loss.
So, if you were to say,
lose $5 this morning,
all right, you had it in your pocket
and you lost it on the way to this lecture,
you would feel exaggeratedly bad about that.
You should really regard $5 as just nothing.
Because the present value of your lifetime income
is in the millions,
so what's $5?
But you don't think that way.
And so, you're spooked and deterred by small losses.
And less encouraged by small gains.
So, this kind of thing allows
business people to exploit people,
if they want to.
If people are so focused
on these little changes,
then you are encouraged in business
to try to pick things out
that people are paying attention to,
like small things,
and sell insurance policies
on just those things.
And so, insurance should be concentrated
on the really big things,
like life insurance.
You know, the fact that
one of your parents,
your children's parents could die,
and the children's family would be
out of money for the rest of their lives.
That's a big thing.
But it may not work
to sell that kind of insurance.
You can do something
that is more focused on what people are watching,
and make it something little,
so that it doesn't require
them to spend so much money.
The classic example of that is funeral insurance.
Okay?
You go around telling people,
if for some reason this sales pitch works,
and it's worked for thousands of years,
they sold this in ancient Rome.
You tell people,
you know, if someone in your family dies,
you could have an expense of getting a proper burial
for this person.
It costs money.
And so, they would insure that one thing.
Okay?
And it was a little thing.
But it works to sell that.
Another example of that is airline flight insurance.
Okay?
You are insured for this flight on the airplane.
I heard an ad for funeral insurance recently.
They're still doing this after 2,000 years,
because it still works.
And it's manipulative.
That's not what you should do for people.
You should not pick out some little thing.
They also have diamond ring insurance.
After an engagement,
some women will want to buy an insurance policy
on the diamond,
because it can actually fall out of your ring,
and you lose it.
But that's like,
what is it, $5,000, something.
It's not big.
It's not essential.
And if you're insuring that and not other things,
you're making a mistake.
But fortunately, the insurance industry is not too,
it has come around to do things that are more.
They are doing things that matter and are big.
And that's because this Kahneman-Tversky value function
is an aspect,
it represents an error that people are prone to.
And it's not just a matter of,
I'm not sure that people are prone to be making,
but it's not total and not complete.
And so, ultimately, people don't go to insurance companies
that manipulate them.
It gets around.
And eventually, people come around wanting something better.
And so, while there is some manipulation, it's limited.
The other aspect of Kahneman-Tversky
is the weighting function.
Okay.
And I'm going to draw, again, a picture of it.
And it's this time, it's how people psychologically
think about probabilities.
And this, again, is Kahneman-Tversky.
A probability is a number between 0 and 1,
or 0 and 100%.
I'll put 0 here and 1 here.
We can tell someone the probability of something,
but they can't accept it psychologically.
The errors that people make
are described by the weighting function.
What the weighting function is,
the psychological impact.
You are behaving as if you don't understand the probability.
So, what Kahneman-Tversky say
is that for very low probabilities,
people may round them to 0.
And for very high probabilities,
they may round them to 1.
But if they decide not to
round them to 0 or 1,
they exaggerate the difference between 0 and 1.
You just can't think in
terms of a continuum of probabilities.
So, this is what the weighting function,
this is the weight as a function of the probability.
For low probabilities, it's 0.
I'm going to maybe exaggerate it here.
Then it jumps up.
And it's something like,
it's something like this.
And as it gets close to 1,
it jumps up to 1 again.
So, you see, it's like a broken line segment.
And there's been various versions of this theory,
but this is the simplest version of it.
So, that means,
if you're getting on an airplane,
you think, well, what's the probability
of this airplane crashing?
Well, you know, it's probably something like
1 in 10 million or even less than that.
So, what's the probability
of this plane crashing?
Well, most of us in our mind just say,
it's 0 and I'm done.
I'm not going to think about it.
I'm not going to worry about it.
And so, we're down here.
We've rounded it to 0.
But some people don't round it to 0, okay?
And for them, they just
blow it out of all proportion
in their minds and it becomes exaggerated.
So, I have it here.
So, it looks like it's a half.
So, this would be 1 here.
And this is about 0.4.
And then, ultimately,
if the probability gets really high,
then I'm not even going to think about it.
It's 1, okay?
So, you know, it's a little bit like people,
in some of the most primitive languages in the world,
there's only a couple of numbers.
There's 0, there's 1,
maybe there's 2 or 3,
and then there's no more numbers.
But our minds are still very primitive
in dealing with probabilities.
So, it's like there's only three probabilities.
Can't happen, maybe,
and will happen, okay?
So, I think airline flight insurance is an example
of trying to manipulate this personality characteristic.
So, it means that they'll catch all the people
who exaggerate it, right?
They used to have vending machines outside of airlines.
The vending machines would encourage you to buy,
just for this flight.
They put it right there
when you're getting on the flight.
And so, that's when you're most nervous,
if you're one of these people who's up here.
And, of course, most people don't buy,
but they don't have to sell it to everybody.
They just sell it to these people,
and they charge an outrageous price.
But I haven't seen these vending machines anymore.
This is interesting.
Economists wrote about them 30 or 40 years ago,
and they used to be everywhere.
And they just kind of disappeared.
Do you ever see one of these?
I think they're gone.
Why is that?
Because people are just like that.
And so, it's not like Kahneman and Tversky
are immutable, representing immutable errors.
These are errors that naturally happen,
but you can get past it.
And you end up wanting
to deal with people you trust.
So, you see some vending machine at the airport,
and you think, well, my insurance agent
isn't recommending I get this.
I've got some kind of insurance.
I'll take that.
I'll go to the airport.
I'll get a new one.
You don't want to get past it.
There's a professor in Germany at the Max Planck Institute
in Berlin, Gerhard Gigerwenzner,
who has been taking on Kahneman and Tversky
and saying that they're right,
that people show these tendencies for errors,
but I can train people
out of them with no problem.
Those errors, I just tell them,
And they don't do it anymore.
Gary Gorton just did a
seminar here on errors that people
make in financial.
No, Nick Barberis here on SOM.
And he was using Caltech students and tested their
ability to prevent certain kind of errors like this.
And he found that even the Caltech students made these
errors just horribly.
We were wondering, aren't they supposed to be bright?
Those are young math geniuses.
But about a third of them got everything right.
So I'm thinking, you know, they're only undergraduates.
By the time they get along,
if they go to college, they're
going to be great.
They'll eventually be trained out of these errors.
But right now, they're behaving just like behavioral
finance says it will.
So anyway, I think that
you will find that prospect theory
explains a lot of things that go on in finance.
But it doesn't explain everything.
And let me move on.
I want to talk about, let me
see, what do I have so many
things to tell you about here.
And I'm thinking about my time.
It's a huge field, behavioral finance.
Let me mention a few other things.
Regret theory is a theory that
is kind of related to Kahneman
and Tversky.
Tversky.
It says that people fear the pain of regret.
There's an old expression, I was kicking myself because I
made some bad decision.
Well, that's a painful experience, when you did
something wrong.
This is represented somewhat in the kink in the prospect
theory value function.
But regret theory says that there's actually a painful
emotion that you're wired not to like to
have made a mistake.
And so, then you end
up designing your life for a
moment, and you end up making a mistake.
And so, you're trying to make
a life around that, and trying
to avoid doing anything that you might regret later.
And it can create problems.
You may make bad decisions, because you're overly worried
about regret.
Gambling behavior.
Anthropologists have reported that gambling occurs in every
human society.
And so, it's one of the human universals.
And not that everyone does
it, but in every society, you'll
find people that do it.
I have a 1974 study.
I found that 61% of U.S. adults actually gambled at
least once for money in that year.
I bet it has gone up.
There's more opportunities for gambling, and it's gone up.
1.1% of men are compulsive gamblers.
And 0.5% of women.
This is another male trait.
Somehow, men are more vulnerable to compulsive
gambling than women.
But it's only a factor of 2 to 1.
But it's an addiction that happens that distorts people's
thinking.
And it's such an addiction that we have an organization
called Gamblers Anonymous that helps people with this.
It ruins people's lives.
People end up getting a divorce, because you can't
stay with someone, married to someone, who is squandering
the family money.
They do it.
They end up sneaking around to gamble, like drinkers sneak
around for the next drink.
Gambling behavior, it seems to be associated psychologically
with a self-image, a sense of
who I am and why I'm an
important and good person, a sense of competence.
Most gamblers do things that they think are really good.
They think a revealing of their competence.
And they tend to pick a
certain form of gambling that they
become psychologically identified with.
And they avoid any other form of gambling.
Gambling behavior is part of
what goes on in the stock
market.
Certain people who have a personality which makes them
particularly interested in gambling find that a life in
gambling is a form of gambling
that can give them the kind
of stimulation.
Gambling behavior, by the way,
is almost like a drug addiction
in a sense, that people who
are depressed may go to a gambling
casino as a way of getting themselves out of the
depression.
They say that when they
walk into the casino, suddenly my
troubles are gone.
I feel invigorated and alive.
I feel like I'm going to die.
And that creates a hormonal difference in them that they
seek.
And it's almost like injecting yourself with something.
So, it's a very hard thing to conquer.
I mentioned before how when the
New York State in 1811 created
the first corporate law that produced a lot of questionable
companies, people then said, this is just gambling.
It's bad.
But the other side of it
is that the same gambling behavior,
it's not usually a pathology.
It's a way of trying
to get people to do something.
And that's the motivation seeking of various aspects of
our psychology that drive us.
What the stock market is, in
some sense, is a way of
channeling this kind of behavior into something
productive, instead of just a game.
And so, they make it very
clear in the stock markets of the
world, this is about business, and this is productive.
The same emotions that, emotional patterns that
are in the stock market, underlie some, this is not
abnormal, it's most people, underlie traits that work out
well.
Okay, the next major thing
I wanted to talk about is
overconfidence.
And psychologists have found that there's a human tendency
to overestimate one's own abilities.
Okay?
We all think, not all of us.
Most of us think we're above average.
Some of us think we're way above average.
And this tendency has been revealed in a number of
experiments.
I thought I would try one on you.
I don't know if it will work.
I'll try it on this class.
If you will participate in this
experiment by a show of hands.
I'm going to ask you, I have three questions here.
And I want to ask you to,
I'm going to ask you to, I'm going
to ask you to write down a 90% confidence interval.
All right.
Okay, do you have a pencil to write this down?
And then afterwards, I'm going to
tell you the answer and see
if it fell in your confidence interval.
Okay.
So, this is what it is.
What is a 90% confidence interval?
It's a range of values.
So that you are 90% sure that you're overconfident.
You're 90% sure that the
true value lies in this range.
Okay?
So, if I asked you for
what is the population of New Haven,
you might say 90% confidence interval, that's between 50,000
and 150,000.
That means you're 90% sure
that the population falls in that
range.
And so, you should be right 90% of the time.
That if I ask you to
give 90% confidence intervals, you should
be right nine times out of 10.
If I ask for a 99%
confidence interval, you have to widen the
interval, then you should be
right 99 times out of 100.
So, what I'm going to ask you
to do, if you will cooperate with
me, is give 90% confidence intervals for, I have three
questions I'm going to give you.
But I have to ask you to be honest.
Otherwise, this thing won't work.
You could game me by just giving excessively wide confidence
intervals, right?
And then, you know, from zero to infinity.
Then you'll always be right.
But you're not playing honestly.
So, I have to appeal to
your character to do this honestly.
Okay?
So, I have three questions here.
I just changed the questions.
The first is, now, what you
have to write down on your
notepaper somewhere is your honest estimate of a 90%
confidence interval.
And so, the first question is, the world population.
How many people are alive in the world?
All right.
As of, I think it was
8 a.m. this morning, the U.S. Census
has something called the World Population Clock.
And just go, don't cheat.
Some of you have laptops.
Don't do it.
But after this, you can search.
Google on World Population Clock, and it shows you
minute by minute how many
people there are in the world.
Every birth and death.
They're not actually recording them.
It's a fake.
But, I mean, it's supposed to be an estimate.
So, I got the world population.
So, what I want you to do,
can you write down a lower bound
and an upper bound for the world population this morning
as measured by the U.S. Census?
Okay.
Can you write that down?
But I don't want you to make it too wide.
Remember, I only want you to be 90% sure.
And I don't want you to
make it too narrow, because then you're
more likely to fail.
So, you've written that down, the world population?
Okay.
My next question is to the world.
What does it weigh?
Okay.
Well, actually, it's the mass in kilograms of the world.
Can you write that down?
This is astronomy.
Okay.
Let me say, I'm asking for it in kilograms.
But you can do it in metric tons.
That just knocks off three zeros.
A metric ton is 1,000 kilograms.
Okay.
And just so you'll know for
sure, that's not the same thing
as a long ton, which is UK.
The United Kingdom uses the long ton, which is 2,250.
So, the metric ton is roughly 2,000 kilograms.
The metric ton is roughly 1.1 metric tons.
And it's not exactly the same as
a short ton, which we use in
the United States, which is 2,000 pounds, which is 0.98
metric tons.
All right.
Just tell me how many tons.
That's not going to affect
your 90% confidence interval, right?
Just tell me how many tons does the Earth weigh.
Okay?
And then, that's the third.
Second question.
So, how many languages are there in the world?
Now, I know, because you might
complain, this is a matter of
definition, because sometimes two dialects might be
considered a separate language.
Well, I'm asking you to give me the number.
The World Authority on Languages is an organization
that has a website called ethnolog.com.
And if you go to that website, they're always
discovering new languages.
They keep track of it.
New languages keep getting discovered, because some guy
is hiking out in Siberia, and
they go to this little village
and say, hey, these people are speaking
of a different language.
And they say, well, this is
a language that would never have
been documented before.
So, it's this process of learning languages.
They also keep dying out, because they're just elderly
people in this village, and
when they die, you know this
language is going to die with them.
So, anyway, the question is, I want your 90% confidence
interval for the number of languages as defined by
ethnolog.com.
You have to guess how they define a language.
But you have an idea, more
or less, what a language is, right?
It's more than a dialect, because they can still
understand each other if they speak different dialects.
We're talking about really different languages.
OK, have you written down three confidence intervals?
OK, so I'm going to write
down the answers, and I hope this
works.
I'm trusting to your honesty
in getting these things, because
you could game me and make this not work.
But give me your honest confidence.
So, I'm going to write down the correct answer.
So, the world population is 100,000 people.
That's the number of languages.
So, I'm going to write down the correct answer.
So, the world population, as of
8 a.m. this morning, was 6,901,330,581.
OK, now, can I get a
show of hands, how many people's
confidence interval includes that number?
OK, does someone tell me what the number is?
I don't know what percent that is.
That is not 90%.
You're doing pretty well, though.
What do you think, Oliver?
Think it's 80?
See them up again.
Maybe it is 80.
All right, you're doing really well.
Some honest people here didn't put their hands up.
Good.
All right, well, that's one.
So, we did 80 instead of 90.
What about the weight of the Earth in kilograms?
Well, it's 90.
OK, so, that's 80.
So, that's 80.
OK, I want to know what that urine number is.
Item number Multipopular is 5.974 times 10 to the 24th
power.
And I'll give you that in tons, in more familiar.
It's 5,974 billion billion tons.
OK, got that?
We might have to do some calculation.
This would be 5.974 times 10 to the 18th power.
OK, can we do a show
of how many people are in the
confidence interval there?
All right, Oliver, what do you think?
What's the fraction?
5%, maybe 10%.
10%, OK.
So this one, you did really well on world population.
The last one, how many languages are in the world?
Well, according to ethnologue.com, there are 6,909
languages this morning.
OK, how many people got that within their confidence
interval?
OK, what do you think, Oliver?
10%, OK.
Why did you do so much better on world population?
Well, thank you for being honest with me.
I think it worked once again, the overconfident.
So why is it that people are overconfident like this?
And psychologists have tried.
They've tried to describe what
it is that goes on in
people's minds that produces answers like this.
One of them is that people
seem to have a sense that they
understand the world more than they really do.
It's an illusion.
Actually, the world is just infinitely complicated, and
there are so many surprises.
You have a, when you
think about a question like this,
there's many different perspectives that you can take.
And I think that's a good question.
And if you thought more
about it, your imagination might help
you to widen your confidence interval.
But you can't think of all the perspectives at once.
And so, you tend to gravitate
to the first one that comes to
mind, and it gives you an underestimate of the
confidence.
So, that is overconfidence.
By the way, I think it's
a little bit higher in males
than females.
I didn't do a separate male-female count.
But females are definitely overconfident.
That's a so-called macho personality that's supremely
overconfident.
That's not in DSM-IV, but I
don't think it is, but it is
more common among males.
But it's really, everyone is overconfident.
So, there's no important sex difference here.
Incidentally, I think that overconfidence, and this is an
important phenomenon.
It goes beyond yourself.
It extends to your friends.
There's a tendency for people
to think that I have very
smart friends.
I was reflecting the other day,
when I was an undergraduate at
University of Michigan.
I was in the honors program,
and we thought we were pretty
smart.
I had a number of young
people that I just imagined were
heading toward careers.
And they were really great careers.
There was one student that we called young Jack Kennedy.
Because, you know, this was some years ago.
Jack Kennedy was President of the United States.
We thought he was a genius.
That was probably wrong, too, right?
None of these people are geniuses.
I was thinking that most of
my friends ended up in very, you
know, good careers, but nothing that you would think
was spectacular.
I had one friend as an
undergrad, who I thought was a
genius.
His name was Bruce Wasserstein.
Anyone ever heard of him?
Maybe not.
Well, see, that's it.
But he founded his own investment bank called
Wasserstein Perella.
It became really rich.
And then he bought interest in Lazard Frere, the French
investment bank.
And he was a real big shot on Wall Street.
I met him again about 10 years ago.
And then he died.
God.
He had a heart attack and died.
So, I know his whole life.
I saw him when he was 18.
And I've watched his whole life, and it's now history.
It's kind of scary.
But I remember thinking he
was a genius as an undergrad.
But I was wondering, what was wrong with my judgment?
Why did I see so many other geniuses?
And he may be – I thought he
– now that I think back on it,
he had a sort of
real-world common sense that amazed me.
And I thought, well, I'm going
to go to the United States.
I'm going to – I'm going to
try to go to the United States.
But it was a really powerful thing.
I thought it was very powerful.
I think he was smart.
He did some amazing things.
I'm not doing this for you.
I'm just saying, he – he just
knew things that – it wasn't fake knowledge.
He seemed to know how things worked.
So, I guess I was right about one of them.
But not enough that you – none
of you have heard of him, right?
And he was – he has
an investment bank named after him, right?
You should have heard of him, but maybe not.
But anyway, this thing affects people's thinking, too.
I think that we tend to think that the
head of state who's running, the head of our central
bank is a genius.
And this was a genius, because you can do this.
And I think that's what we're trying to do.
But anyway, this thing affects people's thinking, too.
I think that we tend to think
that the head of a state who's
running, the head of our central bank is a genius.
And this really clouds our thinking.
It's not just confidence.
It's like our ego extends
to the other people that we
associate with ourselves.
Now, the head of a
central bank in another country we
have no respect for.
It's only in our own country.
And that's what produces this overconfidence.
So, this tendency for overconfidence produces a lot
of anomalies and opportunities for manipulation.
So, for example, Rakesh Khurana, who is a professor at
the Harvard Business School, has written a book called
Search for the Charismatic CEO.
And he claims that there's
a tendency for people to think
that CEOs are geniuses, or at
least, the one that we found
is a genius.
And companies then seek out a
genius CEO to put in charge of
the company, as a kind of manipulation of the stock
market.
They think, if we got some
guy who has run other companies
He must be a genius.
Put him in our company,
our stock price will go up.
Then we can sell our executive, we can exercise our
options and make a lot of money by putting in
this fake genius.
And Khurana says, well, there
are some people who are maybe
geniuses at management, but most of the time, they're just
lucky, and we tend to develop overconfidence.
And then what happens, according to Khurana, is you
put in some guy who turned around some company
spectacularly, supposedly.
You bring him in to run
a new company, and he doesn't know
anything about this new company.
But he has to justify himself.
So he lays off a lot
of people and shuffles things around and
just destroys everything in the company and ruins things.
This is related to another author that I recommend.
I mentioned him before, I think.
He's a great author.
He's a great writer.
Nassim Taleb wrote a book called Fooled by Randomness.
He's Lebanese, but now in
the U.S. Nassim Taleb, Fooled by
Randomness, that says that most of the things that
happen in life are just chance.
And we tend to believe in chance.
We tend to ascribe them.
If they happen to us,
we conclude, we're very quick to
conclude that it's a sign of our own genius.
And if it happens to someone
that is a friend of us, then
you think, well, I have genius friends.
Isn't that nice?
And so it leads to mistakes.
OK, let me go to another,
how much time do I have?
Cognitive dissonance.
This is another one.
I'm going to go to another one.
I'm going to go to another psychological principle.
The term was coined by sociologist Leon Festinger in
the 1950s, I believe.
I actually met this guy.
That's the nice thing about being in academia.
You meet all these great names, if you're in long
enough, eventually.
But what is cognitive dissonance?
It's a judgmental bias.
It's a belief that people
tend to make, because they don't
want to admit they're wrong.
Maybe I'm oversimplifying this mistake.
It's painful to think that I believed
something and it was wrong.
So people will cling to
old beliefs and try to find
evidence that supports their belief, because they have an
ego involvement with the belief.
And so I will be biased.
The famous experiment indicating cognitive dissonance, done by
some psychologist, is the one that people make.
And it's called the Ego Experiment.
This experiment was done by a couple of people.
This experiment was done by a couple of scientists.
They had the following form.
They got a list of people
who had just bought a car.
And they knew what make of car.
They got their list from car dealers.
So they knew exactly what car they had just bought.
And they called these people up and
asked them to participate in a psych experiment.
Or they said a marketing experiment.
But they didn't let them know that
they knew what car they had just bought.
And then they said, the experiment was the following.
Let's go through a number
of, what magazines do you read?
And they said, let's get these out.
And they said, let's look
through page by page and tell
us which ads you remember reading.
And what they found is that
people read the ads for the
car they just bought.
And they avoided, especially, the car that they thought they
might buy but decided not to buy.
So after you buy a car, you want to confirm
your belief in it.
So you selectively get information that
confirms your belief.
And so this cognitive dissonance is another factor.
It's been demonstrated.
It's an error that people make.
It doesn't mean that people, again, again, none of these
errors is inviolable.
People will make the error, and then they'll learn from
their mistakes, and they'll correct it.
They're not totally cognitive dissonant, but it's just a
kind of error that keeps coming up.
So I'll give you a couple of examples of cognitive
dissonance and its effects on finance.
So, let's look at this.
So, Will Getzman is a professor here at the Yale
School of Management.
And a couple of his co-authors found that mutual fund
investors, when a mutual fund does very badly in its
investment performance, many or most investors sell the
stock and get out of it.
But some of them hang on.
And they thought that that was due, perhaps, to cognitive
dissonance.
Because I bought this fund.
I don't want to sell, because I was right.
So, what they did is, they interviewed these people, and
they found out that these people didn't even know how
badly the fund has done.
They had blocked it out.
And they had an exaggerated impression of the success,
which is characteristic of cognitive dissonance.
You just forget the evidence that's contrary to your theory.
And you keep assembling evidence that
supports your theory.
I have another example of cognitive dissonance.
And this one was produced
by a Professor Sandeel Mullinaithan
at the Harvard Economics Department.
And Mullinaithan looked at financial events.
And he said, well, I don't know.
I don't know.
I don't want buyers.
I want me trying to invest,
because I like it in my
research.
And he butchered it all wrong.
He wanted to keep it all, even though he's very
good at desirable outcomes.
And here, what he says
is, one person had entered this
venture.
And this person was asked
about the value of the fund.
And he thinks that a lot of
people can do it, but I mean,
he's asking the questions.
And then that person gets started.
So, at some point, a
couple of people got the fund.
But the different actors would present their existing
portfolio differently.
In other words, you'd go to
the advisor and you'd say, I
have a portfolio of investments, and I'm almost
entirely in money market funds.
That's all.
You just say that.
You wouldn't express any opinion at all.
Another actor would go and
say, I've got all of my
portfolio in tech stocks.
Or I've got all of my portfolio in options.
Now, what should advisors tell people?
Well, if they were acting really professionally, they
should question the assumptions that made the
actor, supposedly, put all of
their money in one kind of
investment.
And many of the financial advisors did, but usually,
they didn't.
They didn't question the actor.
They assumed that the actor was
the person who had put, supposedly, all of the
investments in money market funds, was someone who was
very risk-averse or thought that
was the right thing to do.
And they didn't want to challenge them.
So, they would walk out
of there with maybe a slightly
different mix of money market funds.
And somebody else who was
in a very risky portfolio, they
didn't challenge them.
They even sent actors in with a very different portfolio.
And they were not the ones who made the decisions.
They were the ones who made the decisions.
And they were not the ones who were very
risk-averse.
And they didn't put all of
their money in one kind of
investment.
They were very risk-averse.
And they were not the ones
who worked with almost all of
their portfolio in their own company's stock.
Now, if you work for Ford
Motor Company, I know this is
my uncle, I had conversations
with him about this, who worked
for Ford Motor Company and put
all of his life savings in Ford
And I've worked at Ford all my life.
They treat me well.
I believe in them.
I'm not going to sell.
And so there's lots of people like that.
So when they show up
at a financial advisor, the first
thing that they should do, the financial advisor should tell
them, get out of your Ford style.
That's just too risky.
And it's a good thing.
It's a good thing.
But it's not going to work.
If you get out of your
Ford style, that's just too risky.
But only 40% of the financial advisors did that.
The 60% left them mostly in their own company stock.
Why did they do that?
Well, Mull and Nathan thought,
it's because the advisors know
there's cognitive dissonance, and they're afraid to drive
away a new client.
Maybe they'll gradually do it over a while.
But you just don't challenge their deep beliefs.
Whatever they say is true.
And so they're kind of yes men.
Not all of them.
And maybe they'll come around.
It relates then again to a moral dilemma.
If you are a financial advisor working in private practice,
what do you do with people who
come to you, if you know from
experience that challenging their deep-seated beliefs will
drive them away?
So in the real world, this
is again, I'm not sure that these
financial advisors are doing the wrong thing.
If they would have
eventually tilt them toward a more responsible portfolio,
they can't drive them away.
So let me list some
of the others and move on.
What else should I talk about?
Anchoring.
Anchoring is a principle that
people, when they're in a job,
they're not going to do it.
They're not going to do it.
So, anchoring refers to a tendency to anchor your
opinions on something that captures your attention.
The famous anchoring experiment by, it was again, Kahneman
and Tversky, they asked, I could almost do this
experiment here in class with you,
if I had a wheel of fortune.
A wheel of fortune is like on a game show.
You spin the wheel, and it
comes up with a number between
zero and 100 in this particular wheel of fortune.
So, this is the experiment.
They asked their subjects, how
many people, it had to be
something that had an answer from zero to 100.
One of their questions was,
how many nations in the world
belong to the United Nations?
Okay.
So, they asked the question, they
said, don't answer me just yet.
Think about that question.
How many?
They said, 100 percent of
nations in the world belong to
the United Nations.
Then they spun the wheel, and
it came up, and it showed a
random number.
And then they asked people for the answer.
Well, it turns out that people
tended to give an answer close
to the number that just came up on the wheel.
This is totally irrational, right?
That wheel has nothing to do
with the answer, and yet people
were influenced by it.
So, then they would follow up
and ask them, hey, that number
you gave is the same as the
one that just came up on the wheel,
and it's got a little
bit of a close to it.
Why did you do that?
The guy would say, just coincidence.
I wasn't influenced by the wheel.
Of course not.
But you know they were, because statistically, they
proved that they were.
So, anchoring means that people are attracted to, they're
affected by subconscious things that, I shouldn't say
subconscious, they didn't make a logical connection.
When you face real ambiguity,
and you don't know the answer,
you've got to come up with
a decision, you are swayed by
the most silly and random things.
There's the representativeness heuristic.
This is also Kahneman and Tversky.
And that is that people overemphasize certain patterns
that they think are representative of what they've
seen before.
So, for example, certain patterns in the stock market
that may be very rare
and unusual, if they remember it,
if it somehow attracted their attention, they begin to look
for that pattern again and again,
and they see it too often.
So, for example, head and shoulders, we talked about that,
that McGee, the technical analyst, he saw the head and
shoulders pattern in the stock
market, and he saw that it
crashed after that.
But actually, it's pretty hard to find those.
They're kind of rare, and it's
not the right way to process
data to be looking for patterns that are representative.
And it invites manipulation.
So, I'll give you some other bad behavior.
If people believe in the
head and shoulders, if they believe
that the head and shoulders pattern of stock price
movements predicts a decline, here's what I can do.
I'll take some thinly traded stock, I'll get a friend,
we'll trade back and forth,
and we'll influence the price to
create, we'll deliberately create a head and shoulders
pattern.
And then we'll short the
stock massively, right at the time
when the head and shoulders pattern would give a sell
signal.
We can make tons of money doing that.
So, why don't we do that?
Well, we don't because it's a manipulation.
Is this thing off?
The battery just died.
I'll talk loud.
Can you hear me through louder talking?
Okay.
I want to then just conclude with social contagion, because
it's so important.
This is my last.
And this is really social psychology.
I'm running out of room here.
That's social contagion.
Social psychology reflects on the fact that people are
interdependent, and what I think is affected by what
others think.
And I think that there's something called herd behavior.
That's a popular term.
It refers to the tendency for
people to move with the herd.
Not consciously.
They don't think that they're moving with the herd.
I might bring up a little sociology here.
And I'll use a term.
Everything has been psychology, but the great sociologist,
one of the founders of the discipline of sociology,
was the French scholar, Emile Durkheim, at the late 19th,
early 20th century.
And he used the word collective consciousness.
And that is that our opinions about what's happening are
formed by a collective understanding of what's
going on.
We think of ourselves, we
have a tendency to think of
ourselves as rational and common sense.
All of our views come from common sense processing of
facts.
I have a sense of belief
about what goes on in the world.
But I underappreciate the extent to which my views are
a little bit arbitrary and shared by millions of people
who are not.
And I think it's very statistically important that
we understand that the idea, that we live in
society is alsoowi
based oneenth time, CO.
The other thing that we can understand is that the
zeitgeist is determined by a collective memory, a collective
set of facts that we operate on.
This herd behavior creates big swings in the stock
market and other things.
So it has huge financial impact.
But anyway, I've listed a number of behavioral finance
principles that really come from psychology.
And I've given some tests
or examples of their proof of
their importance in psychology, in finance.
But what do we conclude from this?
I think that my conclusion
is that we are evolving toward
better and better financial institutions.
There is a lot of manipulation
and exploitation, but we as a
society are not doing that.
We are doing a lot of things.
For example, I mentioned that doing a stock market
manipulation trick to create a head and shoulders pattern.
That is an offense.
Get you in jail for doing that.
And we prosecute that now.
So you can't do that.
I'm going to talk more about this in the next
lecture about regulation.
But it's also people's moral judgments that the people who
evolve to become important in
finance are people who have an
internal compass.
And that's the desire for praiseworthiness that
eliminates this.
I'm going to give just two examples of some recent
articles about this.
In the current issue of the Harvard Business Review, that
I assume is still on newsstands, this is Harvard
Business Review, there's an article by Michael Porter.
And this is a co-author, Mark Kramer.
Porter is a well-known professor at Harvard, in which
he argues that we're coming to
realize more and more about a
principle called, he calls it
shared value, or they call it
shared value.
And that is that the manager of
a company is not going to be,
as I said, a manager of a
company, is not going to be a
manager of a company.
And so, I think, you know, we shouldn't be underestimating
the importance of shared value creation with society, with
other people.
That is, we're all in this together.
And if we're mature, we recognize, for example, that I
don't want to be exploitative.
I don't want to make the
local people in my town upset with
me for telling my clients to become disenchanted.
I don't want those to become disenchanted.
Now, what he's saying is not really about morals exactly,
it's more about long-term value, but I guess morals
somehow creeps into the same judgment.
That mature business people see shared value, and that there
was not enough emphasis on that.
There was too much financial
theory was leading us too much
toward thinking that a manager
should be selfishly pursuing a
normal business.
narrow focus, like maximizing the short-run
value of their shares.
Anyway, the other example I have, which is also recent,
not quite as recent as that,
is a book that came out last
year by Anna Bernasek, who
is actually a journalist, not an
academic, but it's called The Economics of Integrity.
Is that the title exactly?
Yes, right.
Economics of Integrity.
And her point in that book
is that a sense of personal
integrity has dominated what people do in the business
world much more than we thought recently.
There has been too much
disregard for the business world.
There has been too much disregard of the fact that
people do things because they're right.
Well, she gives an example in
the book, and I'll close with
this concept.
She said, let's consider milk.
OK?
Now, you drink milk regularly, I hope.
It's good for you.
But it could poison you.
People used to get sick from drinking contaminated milk.
And you don't ever hear of anyone getting sick.
So she said, why is that?
Because it's the regulation of milk production.
And there are laws about purity of milk.
But when she looked into
it and found that, actually, she
didn't think it was mostly the regulation.
She thought that you are
safe drinking milk because of the
integrity of our people, mostly.
That if you go to some
milk company and talk to the
employees, they may not generally even know about the
regulations. But if you ask them, they might not know.
But if you ask them, they'll
tell you, I mean, are you
careful to keep this milk clean?
They'll tell you, well, someone's going to drink this,
so obviously, it's common sense.
I'll keep it clean.
And what she says, it's not primarily the regulation.
It's the integrity of the people that makes the economic
system work as well as it has.
So anyway, I've emphasized both sides.
I've talked about human failings and about people
exploiting these failings, about people with
antisocial personalities.
But we have a system.
We have a system.
We have a system that somehow eliminates this from
being the major factor in our markets.